A Guide to the Virginia War History Commission, 1915-1931
Library of Virginia
- Series III: Virginia Military Organizations, ca. 1917-1922, 1925
  The Miscellaneous and Correspondence subseries is housed in 1 box and one oversized folder. Noteworthy is the statement of Private John Leedy of the 116th Infantry in which Leedy describes a gas attack in the Meuse-Argonne Valley in October 1918. Also included are statements of service by Major John Izaard, 60th Artillery, Alexander W. Weddell, War Trade Board Delegate to Greece and A.B. Cooke of the American Consulate, Pantros, Greece. There are two groupings of correspondence. The first, spanning 1919 to 1922, documents attempts by Commission member Adjutant General Jo Lane Stern to obtain unit histories from soldiers. Correspondence is both incoming and outgoing and is arranged alphabetically by recipient. There is extensive correspondence from Captain Greenlee D. Letcher, 111th Field Artillery, 29th Division, describing his difficulty in obtaining records for his history of the 111th and Major Hierome L. Opie, commenting on his inability to find time to write a history of the 116th Infantry. The second group of correspondence, covering 1925, contains follow-up requests for unit information by Stern in preparation for Source Volume 5, Virginia Military Organizations in the World War.
  This series is divided into five subseries: 29th Division, 42nd Division, 80th Division, Miscellaneous Units and Miscellaneous and Correspondence.
  - Subseries A: 29th Division
    - Virginia National Guard - Overview (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - History of the 29th Division by John A. Cutchins (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - History of the 29th Division by John A. Cutchins (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - History of the 29th Division by John A. Cutchins (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - History of the 29th Division by Recruiting Publicity Bureau (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Operations of the 29th Division, East of the Meuse River, October 1918 - Parts I and II (See Also Oversize) (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Operations of the 29th Division, East of the Meuse River, October 1918 - Part III (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Operations of the 29th Division, East of the Meuse River, October 1918 - Part IV (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - 116th Infantry - Rosters (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - 116th Infantry - Sanitary Detachment (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - History of the 116th Infantry by Samuel G. Waller (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - First Battalion, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - History of the 3rd Battalion, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - History of Headquarters Company, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - History of Supply Company, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - History of the Machine Gun Company, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - History of Company A, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - History of Company B, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - History of Company C, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - History of Company D, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - History of Company E, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 13)
    - History of Company F, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 14)
    - History of Company G, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - History of Company H, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 16)
    - History of Company I, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 17)
    - History of Company K, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 18)
    - History of Company L, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 19)
    - History of Company M, 116th Infantry (Box 35, Folder 20)
    - 111th Field Artillery - History (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Battery A (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Battery B (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Battery C (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Battery D (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Battery E (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Battery F (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - 111th Field Artillery, Rosters of Batteries A, D, E, F and Supply Company (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - 104th Sanitary Train (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - 115th Field Hospital Company (of 104th Sanitary Train) (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - History of the 104th Ammunition Train (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - 115th Ambulance Company (of 104th Sanitary Train) (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - History of the 112th Machine Gun Battalion (Companies B & D) (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - History of Company A, Signal Corps (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Dental History of the 29th Division by Capt. J.M. Hughes (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Subseries B: 42nd Division
    - Brief History of the 42nd Division (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - 117th Trains Headquarters and Military Police (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Journal of Private G.W. Reed of 117th Train Headquarters and Military Police, 1917 April 8-1919 April 5 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Subseries C: 80th Division
    - Brief History of the 80th Division (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - History of the 318th Infantry Regiment (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - 318th Infantry Regiment - Company G (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - 317th Infantry (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - History of the 314th Machine Gun Battalion (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - 319th Ambulance Company (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Medical History of the 80th Division (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - History of the 315th Field Artillery by Denny B. Wright (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - History of the 319th Infantry by Captain Josiah C. Peck (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - History of the 305th Engineers (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Work of the 320th Infantry in the Defeat of the Hun (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Our "E" Story, Officers of E Co., 319th Infantry (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - 80th Division, Report on Operations, Sept. 9th - Nov. 11th, 1918 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - Roster of Headquarters Troop, 80th Division (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Titles for Still Pictures of the 80th Division (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Material - copied from material loaned by A.M. Ely of Philadelphia (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - My Service with the A.E.F. in France by Capt. Melville Oakham, 320th Infantry (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - History of the 155th Field Artillery Brigade (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Operations Report, 159th Infantry Brigade (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Quarter Masters Activities (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Personnel Taken Prisoner of War (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - Captions and Notes to 80th Division Photographs (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - Series of Ten Letters - re History of 80th Division (Box 38, Folder 17)
    - A Message from the Commanding General to the 80th Division re: The Bayonet (Box 38, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 38, Folder 19)
    - Service Magazine, 1921-1922 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Service Magazine, 1923-1924 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Service Magazine, 1925-1927 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified - History of a Battle Operation (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Subseries D: Miscellaneous Units
    - Virginia Coast Guard
      - 60th Regiment - Battery B & F (Box 40, Folder 1)
      - History of Fifth Virginia Coast Artillery and Battery B -60th Artillery by Major M.M. Milton (Box 40, Folder 2)
      - 35th Regiment (formerly 10th-14th Virginia Coast Artillery) (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - 8th Company (formerly 4th Co. Virginia Coast Artillery) (Box 40, Folder 4)
      - 10th Company (formerly 3rd Co. Virginia Coast Artillery) (Box 40, Folder 5)
      - 12th Company (formerly 8th Co. Virginia Coast Artillery) (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Medical Units
      - Base Hospital 45 (Box 40, Folder 7)
      - Base Hospital 45 - Photographs of Nursing Staff (Box 40, Folder 8)
      - Base Hospital 41 (Box 40, Folder 9)
      - History of Section Sanitaire Unie 516 (formerly University of Virginia Ambulance Section) (Box 40, Folder 10)
      - History of Section Sanitaire Unie 517 (formerly University of Virginia Ambulance Section) (Box 40, Folder 11)
      - History of Section Sanitaire Unie 534 (formerly Washington and Lee Ambulance Section) (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Engineer Units
      - 28th Engineering Division (Box 40, Folder 13)
      - 510th Engineers' Service Battalion (Box 40, Folder 14)
      - Roster of 510th Engineers' Service Battalion (Box 40, Folder 15)
      - 511th Engineers' Service Battalion (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - Unused Manuscripts
      - Report of Quarry and Road Work, Base Section No. 1, A.E.F. by Major William L. Lee (Box 40, Folder 17)
      - History of the 830th Aero Squadron (Box 40, Folder 18)
      - Tank Warfare (Box 40, Folder 19)
  - Subseries E: Miscellaneous and Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous Narratives and Reports
      - Orders (Box 41, Folder 1)
      - The U.S. Naval Batteries (Box 41, Folder 2)
      - Statement of Pvt. John Leedy, 116th Infantry (Box 41, Folder 3)
      - Personal Record of Major William Olds, Medical Corps (Box 41, Folder 4)
      - Sketch of Service of Major John Izaard, 60th Artillery (Box 41, Folder 5)
      - Service Record of Frank P. Evans, Major A.G.O. (Box 41, Folder 6)
      - Record of Major Richard G. Lyne (Box 41, Folder 7)
      - Statement of Lt. Robert E. Craighill (Box 41, Folder 8)
      - Statement of Col. Christopher B. Garnett in the War, 24 September 1918 to 8 September 1919 (Box 41, Folder 9)
      - Historical Sketch of Alexander W. Weddell, War Trade Board Delegate to Greece (Box 41, Folder 10)
      - Statement of Services of A.B. Cooke, American Consulate Pantros, Greece (Box 41, Folder 11)
      - Poem: "The Red Cross Bloke" (Box 41, Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous List of Publications in Files, etc. (Box 41, Folder 13)
      - Unidentified Narrative of Women in the Great War, nd (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1922
      - A-J (Box 41, Folder 15)
      - L-O (Box 41, Folder 16)
      - P-W (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1925
      - B-W (Box 41, Folder 18)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 41, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Virginia's Camps and Cantonments, ca. 1917-1919
  The Virginia Camp and Cantonments series is housed in 4 boxes and is arranged into six (6) subseries. Subseries have been designated for Camp A.A. Humphreys, Fort Hunt, Camp Lee, Quantico, Chesapeake Bay Area Histories and Miscellaneous Narratives and Reports. The most extensive information in this series concerns Camp Lee, located near Petersburg, Virginia. This series contains histories and information about the construction of Virginia's World War I military camps. Many of these records are described in Virginia War History Commission, Supplement No. 3, Calendar of Military Histories, Narratives and Reports (July 1921 issue of Virginia Magazine of History and Biography) and Supplement No. 4, Lists and Calendars of Source Material (October 1921 issue of Virginia Magazine of History and Biography).
  The Camp A.A. Humphreys subseries is housed in 1 box and contains two histories of the construction of Camp A.A. Humphreys (now known as Fort Belvoir): "Illustrated History of Camp A.A. Humphreys" by Captain Charles T. DeRell and "History of Camp A.A. Humphreys" by Colonel Richard Park. Both histories focus on the construction of the camp and include photographs and maps.
  The Fort Hunt subseries is housed in folder and includes a questionnaire that provides an historic overview of the fort as well as a map of the facility.
  The Camp Lee subseries is housed in two boxes. The records include items describing the history of medical care, the Red Cross and welfare work (Knights of Columbus, Jewish Welfare Board and YMCA) at Camp Lee. Also included is a variety of ephemera such as Thanksgiving and Christmas cards and programs, a song book used in Camp Lee YMCA Meetings, and miscellaneous Camp Lee forms and broadsides. Records of note include photographs and post cards of Camp Lee and the first three issues of The Musket (vol. 1, 15 February 1919, vol. 2, 1 March 1919, and vol. 3, 15 March 1919), the official publication of Infantry Officers' School, Training Center, Camp Lee.
  The Quantico subseries is housed in 6 folders. Records on the Marine Corps Base at Quantico include "A History of Quantico Camp" by H.L. Roosevelt and reports on the medical department, personnel office, post chaplain and the work of the YMCA at Quantico.
  The Chesapeake Bay Area Histories subseries is housed in 10 folders and includes a "History of the Port Embarkation, Newport News, Virginia" by Lt. M.J. Mackler, "Naval Operating Base, Hampton Roads-Its Development" by Rear Admiral A.C. Dillingham that includes a map of the base, and a map of Langley Field.
  The Miscellaneous Narratives and Reports subseries is housed in 4 folders and contains a "Report of Convalescent Camp, Hospital Center, Savenay, France" by R.A. Morison. This record includes photographs of the facility.
  - Subseries A: Camp A.A. Humphreys
    - Illustrated History of Camp A.A. Humphreys by Capt. Charles T. DeRell (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - History of Camp A.A. Humphreys by Col. Richard Park (Chapters I-VII) (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - History of Camp A.A. Humphreys by Col. Richard Park (Chapters VIII-XII) (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - History of Camp A.A. Humphreys by Col. Richard Park (Chapters XIII-XXIII) (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - History of Camp A.A. Humphreys by Col. Richard Park (Chapters XXIV) (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Fort Hunt
    - Questionnaire (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Subseries C: Camp Lee
    - History of Mustering, Camp Lee by Capt. R.W. Mackey (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - History of Auxiliary Remount Depot No. 305, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - History of Utilities Organizations at Camp Lee by Capt. H.W. Jones (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - History of Quartermasters Corps, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - History of Base Hospital at Camp Lee by Capt. C.A. Busheim (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Treatment of Gonorrheal Infection at the Base Hospital Annex by Capt. Alfred Mitchell (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Method of Diagnosis of Syphilis at Base Hospital Annex, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Report of Convalescent Center, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Base Hospital Annex, Camp Lee by Capt. E.G. MacFarland (Box 43, Folder 10)
    - History of the Medical Department at Camp Lee by Major J.S. Graves (Box 43, Folder 11)
    - The Red Cross at Camp Lee by C.C. Pinckney (Box 43, Folder 12)
    - History of the Insurance Office of Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 13)
    - Camp Personnel Office, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 14)
    - History of the 105th Ordnance Depot, Camp Lee by Lt. G.E. Davenport (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Sketch of the Provost Marshall, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 16)
    - Work of the Office of Camp Judge Advocate, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 17)
    - Historical Sketch of Camp Lee YMCA (Box 43, Folder 18)
    - History of the Morale Office, Camp Lee by Lt. Col. D.S. Wilson (Box 43, Folder 19)
    - The Camp Library, Camp Lee by Henry Green (Box 43, Folder 20)
    - The Knights of Columbus at Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 21)
    - The Jewish Welfare Board at Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 22)
    - Chaplains in Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 23)
    - Report of the Line Officers Training Schools from the Declaration of War to the Discontinuance of the Schools... (Box 43, Folder 24)
    - History of the Infantry Central Officers' Training School at Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 25)
    - Report on Infantry Officers' Training School, Camp Lee by Col. H.A. Eaton (Box 43, Folder 26)
    - Materials re Officers' Training School Course, Camp Lee presented by Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. (Box 43, Folder 27)
    - Materials re Officers' Training School Course, Camp Lee presented by Arthur Kyle Davis, Jr. (Box 43, Folder 28)
    - Publication of the Infantry Officers Training School, Camp Lee (Box 43, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Programs/Cards (Thanksgiving, Christmas, etc.) (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Song Book used in Camp Lee YMCA Meetings (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Post Cards/Photographs (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Forms, etc. (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Subseries D: Quantico
    - History of Quantico Camp by H.L. Roosevelt (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Overseas Depot, Marine Barracks, Quantico, Virginia (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - Medical Department, Marine Barracks, Quantico, Virginia by M.L. Mann (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Work of the Personnel Office, Marine Barracks, Quantico, Virginia (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Report of Official Duties, Post Chaplain, Marine Barracks, Quantico, Virginia by E.B. Niver (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - Brief History of the YMCA in Quantico by W.L. Darby (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Subseries E: Chesapeake Bay Area Histories
    - History of the Port of Embarkation, Newport News, Virginia by Lt. M.J. Mackler (part 1 of 2) (Box 45, Folder 7)
    - History of the Port of Embarkation, Newport News, Virginia by Lt. M.J. Mackler (part 2 of 2) (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - History of the Work Under the Department of Port Chaplain, Port of Embarkation, Newport News (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Naval Operating Base, Hampton Roads - Its Development by Rear Admiral A.C. Dillingham (Box 45, Folder 10)
    - History of the Fifth Naval District (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Fifth Naval District (Box 45, Folder 12)
    - Outline Report, Camps and Cantonments in Elizabeth City County, Langley Field by Mrs. John F. Nichols (Box 45, Folder 13)
    - Communication Activities in the Fifth Naval District During the War (Box 45, Folder 14)
    - The Armed Guard in the World War by J. Sydney Fitzgerald (Box 45, Folder 15)
    - History of the Armed Guard Detail, 1 January 1917 to 6 April 1918 (Box 45, Folder 16)
  - Subseries F: Miscellaneous Narratives and Reports
    - Front Royal Bemount Depot and the World War by R.P. Cooke (Box 45, Folder 17)
    - Report from Bureau of Animal Industries, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Front Royal, Virginia (Box 45, Folder 18)
    - Report of Convalescent Camp, Hospital Center, Savenay by R.A. Morison (Box 45, Folder 19)
    - Outline - Elements Entering into Selection and Location of Camp, nd (Box 45, Folder 20)
- Series V: Virginia Schools and Colleges, 1919-1922
  The Virginia Schools and Colleges series is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by the name of the school. This series contains reports of war activities during the World War including home-front contributions made by students (Red Cross work, etc.) and lists of students/graduates who served in the armed forces or were killed. Most of the material consists of brief responses to requests for information on war activities made by Dr. James S. Wilson, a University of Virginia professor and chairman of Commission's Virginia Schools and Colleges section, between 1919 and 1922. Schools that responded were: Augusta Military Academy, Blackstone College for Girls, Blackstone Military Academy, Bridgewater College, Chatham Training School, Christiansburg Industrial Institute, College of William and Mary, Eastern College, Elizabeth College, Emory and Henry College, Episcopal High School of Virginia near Alexandria, Fredericksburg Normal School (now Mary Washington College), Hartshorn Memorial College, Halifax Institute, Hampden-Sidney College, Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute, Harrisonburg State Normal School, Hollins College, Industrial High School (Danville, Va.), Ingleside Seminary, Marion College for Women, Miller Manual Labor School, Newport Training School, Inc., Randolph-Macon Academy, Randolph-Macon College, Rappahannock Industrial Academy, City of Richmond Schools and Colleges, Roanoke College, St. Emma Industrial and Agricultural College, Shenandoah Valley Academy, Southern College, Staunton Military Academy, Stonewall Jackson College, Stuart Hall, Sullins College, Sweet Briar College, University of Richmond, University of Virginia, Virginia College, Virginia Military Institute, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Virginia Union University, Washington and Lee University and Woodberry Forest School.
  Notable records include: a list of graduates and current students who served in the armed forces during the war and a list of those killed-in-action from the College of William and Mary; a 1920 Episcopal High School of Virginia yearbook, Whispers, that includes a list of "Alumni in Service in the World War"; an extensive history of the University of Richmond's activities during the World War; a copy of John S. Patton's 1921 book, The University of Virginia in the World War; and a copy of Joseph Reid Anderson's 1920 book, V.M.I. in the World War.
  Additional records on Virginia's Schools and Colleges may be found in the series' County Source Material and City Source Material.
  - Augusta Military Academy (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Blackstone College for Girls (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Blackstone Military Academy (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Bridgewater College (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Chatham Training School (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Christiansburg Industrial Institute (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - College of William and Mary (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Eastern College (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth College (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - Emory and Henry College (Box 46, Folder 10)
  - Episcopal High School of Virginia near Alexandria (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Fredericksburg Normal School (Box 46, Folder 12)
  - Hartshorn Memorial College (Box 46, Folder 13)
  - Halifax Institute (Box 46, Folder 14)
  - Hampden-Sidney College (Box 46, Folder 15)
  - Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute (Box 46, Folder 16)
  - Harrisonburg State Normal School (Box 46, Folder 17)
  - Hollins College (Box 46, Folder 18)
  - Industrial High School, Danville, Virginia (Box 46, Folder 19)
  - Ingleside Seminary (Box 46, Folder 20)
  - Marion College for Women (Box 46, Folder 21)
  - Miller Manual Labor School (Box 46, Folder 22)
  - Newport Training School, Inc. (Box 46, Folder 23)
  - Randolph-Macon Academy (Box 46, Folder 24)
  - Randolph-Macon College (Box 46, Folder 25)
  - Rappahannock Industrial Academy (Box 46, Folder 26)
  - City of Richmond Schools and Colleges (Box 46, Folder 27)
  - Roanoke College (Box 46, Folder 28)
  - St. Emma Industrial and Agricultural College (Box 46, Folder 29)
  - Shenandoah Valley Academy (Box 46, Folder 30)
  - Southern College (Box 46, Folder 31)
  - Staunton Military Academy (Box 46, Folder 32)
  - Stonewall Jackson College (Box 46, Folder 33)
  - Stuart Hall (Box 46, Folder 34)
  - Sullins College (Box 46, Folder 34)
  - Sweet Briar College (Box 46, Folder 35)
  - University of Richmond (Box 46, Folder 37)
  - University of Virginia (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - University of Virginia (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - University of Virginia (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - University of Virginia (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Virginia College (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Military Institute (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Union University (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Washington and Lee (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - Woodberry Forest School (Box 47, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 47, Folder 12)
- Series VI: County Source Material, 1919-1927